{"tossups": [{"question": "After this event, Hyman Rickover testified that no \u201csimple, easy gimmick\u201d explains why his program had never experienced an event like this disaster. Former Dartmouth President John Kemeny chaired a commission investigating this event. William Scranton falsely reported that Metropolitan Edison claimed that \u201ceverything was under control\u201d after this event, which occurred at a facility named for its distance from Middletown, Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this 1979 accident, the worst nuclear disaster in American history.", "answer": "<b> Three Mile Island</b> nuclear accident (or disaster, meltdown, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this battle, the<em> Marquesa</em> was sent out ahead to prevent attacks from light ships. The fall of the Famagusta colony preceded this battle, which brought an end to one side\u2019s attempt to rescue Cyprus. The<em> Real</em> [ray-AHL] rammed the flagship of Uluc Ali Pasha at the height of this battle. Miguel Cervantes lost an arm in this battle, which was a decisive victory for Don Juan of Austria. For ten points, name this 1571 battle where the Holy League defeated the Ottomans.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Lepanto</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1944, a ship named for this figure ran aground on a sandbank in the Thames Estuary; its masts rise above the water, and it still holds nearly 3 million pounds of live explosives. Benedict Arnold replaced this man as leader of an invasion after he was killed by a burst of grapeshot to the head and thighs, contrary to the musical<em> Hamilton</em>, which claimed he \u201ctook a bullet in the neck in Quebec.\u201d For ten points, name this Irishman who fought for the colonists during the American Revolution, leading the 1775 invasion of Canada.", "answer": "Richard<b> Montgomery</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The \u201cbat-wing\u201d floor plan that once characterized these places was described in the Kirkbride design. After a Quaker woman died in one of these places, William Tuke founded the York Retreat, which developed the \u201cmoral treatment\u201d method used in these places. The reform of jails, schools, and these institutions was promoted by Dorothea Dix before she worked as a nurse in the Civil War. For ten points, name these facilities where patients with disorders like schizophrenia were often abused in 19th century America.", "answer": "<b> psychiatric hospital</b>s (or<b> mental hospital</b>s or<b> mental asylum</b>s; accept<b> insane asylum</b>s; prompt on \u201chospitals\u201d or \u201casylums\u201d) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1957, this musician canceled a Soviet Union tour in solidarity with the Little Rock Nine. Kid Ory was part of this musician\u2019s \u201cHot Five\u201d band, which added Pete Briggs and drummer Al Dodds to become the \u201cHot Seven\u201d in 1927. This man, the first jazz musician to reach the cover of Time magazine, won a Grammy in 1964 for his performance of \u201cHello, Dolly!\u201d For ten points, name this legendary jazz trumpeter and singer of \u201cWhat a Wonderful World,\u201d known as Satchmo.", "answer": "Louis<b> Armstrong</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Jazz"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This city used a luxury tax to keep rents artificially low in public housing projects like the enormous Karl-Marx-Hof during a period from 1918-34 in which this city was nicknamed \u201cRed.\u201d Moritz Schlick organized an influential intellectual group in this city around 1918; that group, which included members like Godel and Carnap, advocated for logical empiricism and was called this city\u2019s Circle. For ten points, name this home city of Sigmund Freud, the capital of Austria.", "answer": "<b> Vienna</b> (or<b> Wien</b>) Page 2", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {"question": "James Mason read this man\u2019s last speech to the senate, which noted the South would \u201cpart in peace\u201dif faced with \u201csubmission or resistance.\u201d This Secretary of State for John Tyler supported the annexation of Texas, and as Vice President, this man drew the ire of Andrew Jackson when his wife Floride ignored the wife of Jackson\u2019s Secretary of War in the Petticoat Affair. With Daniel Webster and Henry Clay, this man formed a triumvirate in the senate. For ten points, name this politician from South Carolina who promoted the doctrine of nullification.", "answer": "John<b> Calhoun</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Soldiers from this former nation plotted to assassinate a losing candidate in Operation Quartz, but his victory meant the operation wasn\u2019t necessary. Abel Muzorewa briefly led a successor state to this entity, and the Lancaster House Agreement ended a longstanding conflict in this country. Forces loyal to this country fought ZANU and ZAPU guerrillas in a civil war known as its namesake \u201cBush War.\u201dRobert Mugabe gained power after the 1979 dissolution of, for ten points, what former African country now known as Zimbabwe?", "answer": "Republic of<b> Rhodesia</b> (accept Colony of<b> Southern Rhodesia</b>; do not accept or prompt on Zimbabwe)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Theophilus Cotton ordered the splitting of this feature in order to allow a portion of it to be displayed more publicly. Alexis de Tocqueville wrote how this feature\u2019s \u201cvery dust is shared as a relic.\u201d Thomas Faunce was the first to describe the legend about this object that John Alden was the first person to have set foot on it. William Bradford\u2019s history surprisingly omits any mention of, for ten points, what physical object where, in 1620, the pilgrims aboard the<em> Mayflower</em> supposedly set foot?", "answer": "<b> Plymouth Rock</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Yakov Zhilinsky was blamed for giving overaggressive orders in this battle. Max Hoffmann predicted that Alexander Samsonov and Paul von Rennenkampf would refuse to help each other during this battle, which was followed by an engagement at the Masurian Lakes. This battle was named after a battle 500 years earlier to \u201cavenge\u201d a loss at Grunwald. Erich Ludendorff rose to fame after, for ten points, what 1914 battle where Paul von Hindenburg defeated a Russian force?", "answer": "(Second) Battle of<b> Tannenberg</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This king\u2019s forces captured Minorca, leading to the execution of John Byng. Robert-Francois Damien\u2019s attempt to kill this man was foiled by his thick winter clothes. This man\u2019s minister Cardinal Fleury punished Jansenist priests, and his mistress supported Enlightenment philosophers like Voltaire. The saying \u201cApres moi, le deluge\u201d or \u201cafter me, the flood\u201d is attributed to, for ten points, what great-grandson of the Sun King, Louis XIV [14]?", "answer": "<b> Louis XV</b> [15]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man annexed Nabatea after the death of its king Rabbel II Soter. This man won the Battle of Tapae before crossing the Danube River, allowing him to capture Sarmizegetusa. In 106 AD, the Dacian Empire was defeated by this man, who brought the Roman empire to its territorial height. This man\u2019s conquests were commemorated in a spiral relief column in the Forum. For ten points, name the second of the Five Good Emperors.", "answer": "<b> Trajan</b> (or Marcus Ulpius<b> Trajan</b>us)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Adam Hochschild alleged that the country ruled by this man underwent a \u201cGreat Forgetting\u201d after his death. A Mark Twain pamphlet titled for this man\u2019s soliloquy</b> <b>publicized the practice of severing human (+)</b> <b>hands that was carried out by this leader\u2019s</b> <b>military force, the Force Publique. The Stokes Affair damaged this ruler\u2019s reputation, as did the Casement Report, which announced the brutal treatment of (*)</b> rubber plantation workers in a state that this leader established during the Berlin Congress. The Congo Free State was ruled by, for ten points, what Belgian king?", "answer": "<b> Leopold II</b> (prompt on Leopold)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Followers of this denomination travel on the Arba\u2019een pilgrimage, one of the largest in the world. That event is part of this denomination\u2019s remembrance of the death of Husayn ibn Ali at the Battle of Karbala, the (+) Mourning of Muharram, which includes the day of Ashura. This denomination, which includes Sevener and Twelver schools, believes that (*) </b>Muhammad appointed his son-in-law Ali as successor. For ten points, name this denomination dominant in Azerbaijan and Iran, the second-biggest denomination of Islam behind Sunni Islam.", "answer": "<b> Shia</b> Islam (accept<b> Shi\u2019i</b>tes)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>To help ease the burden caused by taxes on the financing of these objects, Periandros introduced a system called the</b><em><b> symmories</b></em><b>. Polycrates provided forty of these objects in the Battle of (+) Pelusium. During the First Punic War, these were among the smaller vessels outfitted with a hook-like boarding tool called a</b><em><b> corvus</b></em><b>. One of these vessels provided news of defeat to the (*) </b> Athenians after the Battle of Aegospotami. For ten points, name these ancient ships named for the fact that they had three rows of oars.", "answer": "<b> trireme</b>s (accept<b> triremis</b>; prompt on (ancient Greek) ships or similar answers)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This author wrote a work in which Pope Innocent XII is asked to overturn the conviction of the count Guido Franceschini,</b><em><b> The Ring and the Book</b></em><b>. This author inserted the ironic</b> <b>phrase \u201cGod\u2019s in his heaven, all\u2019s right with the world,\u201d in the (+)</b> <b>\u201cPippa Passes\u201d piece</b> <b>for the</b><em><b> Bells and Pomegranates</b></em><b> series. This author\u2019s most famous poem is suspected to be about Alfonso Il d\u2019Este, the Duke of Ferrera, and his murdered wife Lucrezia d\u2019Medici, whom he describes as having a heart (*)</b> \u201ctoo soon made glad.\u201d For ten points, name this Victorian poet of<em> My Last Duchess</em>, the husband of the author of<em> Sonnets from the Portuguese</em>.", "answer": "<b> R</b>obert<b> Browning</b> (prompt on Browning) Page 9", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>This election year marked the first time a party\u2019s national convention was televised. The winner of this election won support by claiming the 80th Congress had stuck a \u201cpitchfork in the farmer\u2019s back.\u201d During this year\u2019s Democratic convention, 30 (+) southern senators walked out over a civil rights dispute and instead nominated \u201cDixiecrat\u201d Strom Thurmond. In this year, a (*) </b> photograph was taken of a man holding a<em> Chicago Daily Tribune</em> newspaper that incorrectly reported Thomas Dewey as the victor. For ten points, name this year in which Harry Truman won a full term in office.", "answer": "US Presidential election of<b> 1948</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Ziryab introduced toothpaste and deodorant to this peninsula from Baghdad. Hisham II</b> <b>ruled a caliphate on this peninsula where the hajib Al-Mansur secured power. (+)</b> <b>Taifas</b> <b>were independent kingdoms on this peninsula, where Muhammed XII of the Nasrid Dynasty ruled an emirate. Cardinal Cisneros led a (*)</b> campaign against Muslims on this peninsula, which was home to the emirates of Cordoba and Granada. For ten points, name this European peninsula that was the subject of the Reconquista by Christian forces fighting for Spain.", "answer": "<b> Iberia</b>n Peninsula", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In one war, this country favored holding the towns of Ebeltoft and Fredericia to force attackers into a defensive line known as this country\u2019s \u201cearthwork.\u201d This country passed</b> <b>the November Constitution to exert influence over a region it promised not to (+)</b> <b>annex,</b> <b>leading to the violation of the London Protocol and subsequent invasion. After this country was decisively defeated at Dybbol, it surrendered the region of (*)</b> Lauenburg. For ten points, the Treaty of Vienna was signed after an Austrian and Prussian coalition forced what Nordic country to give up Schleswig and Holstein?", "answer": "<b> Denmark</b> ", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A foreign minister of this country led the \u201cMoscow faction\u201d against the \u201cPrison</b> <b>faction.\u201d Ana Pauker helped about 100,000 Jews from this country emigrate to Israel.</b> <b>Petru Groza deposed this country\u2019s monarch (+)</b> <b>Michael I and was replaced by</b> <b>Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej. The final communist leader of this country was (*)</b> executed on Christmas during a 1989 revolution. For ten points, name this Eastern European country where Nicolae Ceausescu [cho-chess-koo] led from Bucharest.", "answer": "<b> Romania</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}